Guide to the John Powell Irish Papers, 1882-1923
Department of Special Collections
John Powell Irish Papers,
1882-1923
Special Collections M033
Irish, John Powell
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of Mrs. Frances I. Hus, Daughter of J.P. Irish, 1928
BIOGRAPHY
John Powell Irish (Colonel), editor, attorney, farmer, law-maker, humanitarian and official was born in Iowa City, Iowa, January 1, 1843. He was educated in the primitive public schools of the frontier. As a young man, Irish was a school teacher and then was admitted to the bar in Iowa before he entered journalism as a profession. For twenty years he was editor of the Iowa State Press. In Iowa he was three times elected a representative to the state legislature, 1869-1872. He married Annie Fletcher in 1872. In 1880 he moved to California where he later was editor of the Times (Oakland) and the Alta California.
Politically, Irish was a "Gold" Democrat and he spoke on economic and financial questions, centering on the sound money and the gold standard viewpoints. In California, Irish became concerned with the treatment of people of Japanese descent living in the United States and he wrote, spoke and acted on the behalf of these people for many years. He founded and organized the American Committee on Justice to further this cause.
John P. Irish was appointed naval customs officer of the Port of San Francisco, 1894, and he was thereafter known as "Colonel" Irish. For twenty-five years Irish was a director of the California Blind Directory Home. He died on October 6, 1923, from an accidental fall when attempting to board a moving streetcar in Oakland, California.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The major portion of the Irish Papers is the correspondence of John Powell Irish, 1882-(1916-1921)-1923. Included in the collection are: the correspondence received by Irish; (not complete) eight items of a biographical nature written by Irish about members of his family and close friends; several legal papers; a scrapbook of editorials, and a book of Irish's speeches, addresses and briefs. In addition, there are articles written by Irish on subjects with which he was closely associated at one time or another during his life.
Of primary interest in the collection are the articles and correspondence written on political subjects such as the Japanese in California, free coinage, woman suffrage and prohibition.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
- Correspondence outgoing
  Letters of John P. Irish arranged chronologically: Feb. 6., 1889 through 1922; also undated letters of John P. Irish arranged alphabetically.
- Correspondence Incoming
  Letters to John P. Irish arranged alphabetically by author or signer and ordered chronologically under each signer or author; also letters relating to J. P. Irish arranged alphabetically by author or signer. Includes related correspondence.
- Biographical Data
  Biographical data about family members and close friends of Irish.
  Arranged alphabetically by the subject of the biographies.
- Articles
  Articles written by J. P. Irish arranged alphabetically by the subject of the articles and under each subject the articles are arranged alphabetically by the titles of the articles.
- Legal Documents
  Arranged alphabetically by title or subject and then chronologically under each signer or author.
- Newspaper Clippings
  Newspaper clippings, dated, are arranged chronologically, followed by newspaper clippings, undated. A scrapbook of newspaper editorials, presumably written by Irish, 1900-1923, is after these.
- Printed Material
  A bound volume titled Speeches, Addresses, Arguments and Briefs contains speeches, etc., by Irish. Then follows other printed matter, including a few pamphlets and printed circulars.
- Miscellany
  A folder of miscellaneous items.
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence: Outgoing
  - Feb. 6, 1889--May 6, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Feb. 6, 1903--Jan. 31, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Feb. 24, 1910--1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jan. 30, 1911--Dec. 31, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jan. 6, 1913--1913 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - July, 1914--1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jan. 28, 1916--Aug. 2, 1919, and 1919 n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jan. 29, 1920--Sept., 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oct., 1920--Nov., 1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1920:Argonant--Greenbie (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1920:Harvey--Wilson (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jan., 1921--June, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - July 1, 1921--Nov. 24, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Nov., 1921--1921 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Feb. 28, 1922--June 22, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - July 10, 1922-1922 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Undated: California -- The Register (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Undated: Saturday Evening Post -- The Yale Review (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Correspondence: Incoming
  - Adams, E.D.--Marble, M. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Parker, G.F.--Wyman, J.B. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Related Correspondence: Foote, W.W.--Morton, S. (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Biographical Data
  - Dodge, A.C.--Wagner, A.I. (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Articles
  - American Legion: (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "A Word to the American Legion"
    - "A Word with the American Legion"
  - Farming: (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Five articles concerning the farmer and his position in relation to the government.
    - "Farming in the Delta"
  - Foreign Countries: (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - "Central American Union"
    - "Guatemala's Public Schools"
  - Government Employees: "The Federal Clerks" (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Iowa: (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - "Early Journalists of Iowa"
    - "Founding of the University of Iowa"
    - "A History of the University of Iowa"
  - Japanese Question in California: (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - "The Arts of the Agitators"
    - "California and the Japanese"
    - "When They Come"
    - "Anti-Japanese Agitation in California"
  - The Japanese Question: (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "Fore Word"
    - "The Japanese as an Economic Necessity"
    - "For the Japanese New World"
    - "On Nullification"
    - "Race Prejudice"
    - "The Races in the Delta"
    - "Review of the Court's Decision in the Anti-Japanese Land Lease of Washington"
    - "A Review of Dr. Wheeler's Anti-Japanese Speech"
    - "The Stolen Letters of Senator Phelan"
    - "Wilson's Alien and Sedition Law"
  - The Japanese Question: (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "Hearings of the Investigating Committee in the U.S. House of Representatives"
    - "Immigration"
    - "Japanese Question"
    - "Japanese Question"
    - "Japanese Question"
    - "Japanese Question"
    - "Japanese Question"
    - "Phelan and Kawahawi Letters"
    - "Purpose of the Anti-Japanese Investigation"
    - "Treaty, U.S. and Japan"
  - Political: (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "Notes on Irish and the Third Party Movement"
    - "The Campaign and State Senator Case"
  - Prohibition: (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "Prohibition and Religion"
    - "Prohibition and Property Rights"
  - Religion: "Religious Liberty" (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - The Silver Standard: "On the Silver Standard" (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Stockton: (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "Stockton"
    - "Suggestions for an Ordinance Providing for Sanitary Disposal of City Waste"
  - Taxation: (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "Again, the Single Tax"
    - "Taxation in California"
  - Woman Suffrage: (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "Woman Suffrage in California"
    - "Women in Politics"
  - The Water Problem: (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - "Mt. Hamilton Water Shed"
    - "In Re: Water Companies"
- Legal Documents (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Delta Association vs. The Diverters of the Kings River into the San Joaquin Case, Summary of
  - Platform and principles of the Democratic Party
  - "On the Eight Hour Law"
  - On the Pond Case
  - Pond Case, Power of Attorney
  - To the Reclamation Board; Matter of Rejoinder
  - Smith Case, Brief of
  - Union Fish Case
  - Witnesses' Sworn Affidavit to the Whereabouts and Sobriety of John P. Irish on Sept. 25, 1880
- Newspaper Clippings
  - Jan. 12, 1882--Oct. 4, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Jan. 1, 1897--Feb. 1, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Feb. 1, 1904--1910 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Aug. 31, 1911--Oct. 15, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Undated,random order (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Scrapbook of editorials in newspapers, presumably written by J.P. Irish: 1900-1923 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Printed Material
  - Bound volume titled "Speeches, Addresses, Arguments and Briefs" by John P. Irish. Dedicated "To my daughter Frances. Jno P. Irish. Dec. 25th 1912." Contents: (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Poem: "The Story of a Dinner Plate"
    - Frontispiece: Photo of J.P. Irish
    - Brief Biography of J.P. Irish
    - "Memorial Address on Governor Bartlett", Feb. 6, 1889
    - "Gold and Silver: The Case Stated", April 28, 1893
    - "Single Standard and Sound Money", August 15, 1895
    - "A Speech by J.P. Irish to the National Democratic Convention", 1896
    - "International Arbitration: United States and Salvador...Opening Statement", April 1, 1902
    - "Arbitration between the United States and The Republic of El Salvador...Closing Argument and Summary", April 19, 1902
    - "In the Matter of the Arbitration between the Republics of the United States and Salvador: Protocol, Opinion and Award", May 8, 1902
    - "Land Leasing", March 5, 1902, (unbound, but kept loose in the volume)
  - Other Printed Matter: (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - The Palimpsest, April, 1921.Contains "A Reminiscence", by John P. Irish
    - "The Old Time Edition," by John P. Irish, 1914
    - "Committee Opposing the Anti-Japanese Initiative" pamphlet
    - "Roosevelt Memorial Exercises", Feb. 9, 1919, 2 copies
    - "National Woman Suffrage Association", 1880,circular., Irish (?) notes on back in pencil.
- Miscellany: (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Unidentified letter
  - Unidentified fragment of a letter
  - Calling card of Col. John A. Joyce
  - Copy of the minutes of an unidentified meeting
  - List of the members of the American Committee of Justice